<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dovvnfall of the pretended divine authoritie of the hierarchy into the Sea of Rome from some arguments and motives, to the finall extirpation of that unlawful government of the prelacy : as having no foundation in the Scriptures, but onely in that filthy dung-hill of by V.N.V.</title>
            <author>V. N. V.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1331</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12773547</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12773547</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93696</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64760)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 253:E160, no 3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dovvnfall of the pretended divine authoritie of the hierarchy into the Sea of Rome from some arguments and motives, to the finall extirpation of that unlawful government of the prelacy : as having no foundation in the Scriptures, but onely in that filthy dung-hill of by V.N.V.</title>
                  <author>V. N. V.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93696:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93696:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DOVVNFALL OF THE PRETENDED Divine Authoritie of the Hierarchy into the Sea of ROME. <hi>FROM</hi> Some Arguments, and Motives, to the finall Extirpation of that unlawfull government of the PRELACY: as having no foundation in the Scriptures, but onely in that filthy dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill of the Canon Law of the Popes Authoritie, and therefore Antichriſtian. <hi>And</hi> So they are wrongfully blamed for abuſe of their offices, the very nature and right uſe whereof is to overthrow Churches and Kingdoms, Laws of God &amp; man, to propagate the kingdom of Antichriſt: the office is ſo bad as cannot be uſed otherwiſe. <hi>Alſo their dangerous practiſes diſcovered: and the great Objection of Martyr-Prelates anſwered.</hi> By <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. N. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>I know thy works, and thy labour, and patience, and how thou canſt not endure them which are evill, and thou haſte tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles and are not, and haſte found them lyers. <bibl>
                     <hi>Apoc. 2.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Oſtentantes ſe ſe quaſi ſint paſtores eccleſiae, quaſi ſint Epiſcopi cum ſint merae umbrae, perſonae lupercales, ſtatuae mutae, &amp; picturati trunci.</p>
               <p>Sub magnifico Epiſcoporum titulo, totum Mundum perdentes.</p>
               <bibl>Luther: de falſo nom: &amp; ordine Epiſcoporum. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> Vitebergae. p. <hi>330.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Anno ReX ChrIstVs, Vt VerVs, regnVM papae DeſtrVet.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:93696:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93696:2"/>
            <head>Ad Chariſſ: ſuum, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. N. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>PAſtorum in orbe cernimus</l>
               <l>Ovilis Chriſti copiam:</l>
               <l>Pauci ah! quibus corde Dei</l>
               <l>Eſt gloriae meditatio:</l>
               <l>Sed ventris eſſe plutimos</l>
               <l>Britannae paſtores, magis</l>
               <l>Videmus addictos papae</l>
               <l>Traditionibus impijs:</l>
               <l>Cujus ſuperbos ſpiritus</l>
               <l>Sic, qui induerunt at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> opes</l>
               <l>Ejus relictas poſſident</l>
               <l>Quas devorant voraciter:</l>
               <l>Queîs imminent regaliter:</l>
               <l>Et veritatis deprimunt</l>
               <l>Veros patrones, &amp; Dei</l>
               <l>Veri timentes opprimunt</l>
               <l>In gratiam niſi papae</l>
               <l>Sui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> commodi, &amp; ſui</l>
               <l>Honoris eminentiae.</l>
               <l>Sed ipſa quae fluunt Dei</l>
               <l>Ex fonte verbi Limpido</l>
               <l>Hos judicant, hos comprobant,</l>
               <l>Antiſtites papae imperî,</l>
               <l>Qui templa tot deglutiunt</l>
               <l>Qui templa tot tot devorant.</l>
               <l>Ne quis per illos devius</l>
               <l>Aberret à Dei via</l>
               <l>Fugiat<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tales impios</l>
               <l>Et faſtuoſos clericos</l>
               <l>Falſoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> paſtores procul.</l>
               <l>procul.</l>
               <l>procul.</l>
               <l>In gratiam ſcripſit</l>
               <l>Inanes Arce viros.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93696:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>COURTEOUS READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF duty to Religion and Subjects liberties; if loyalty to ſoveraigne Authoritie; if long and heavy preſſures un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the enemies of all theſe may challenge any privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge at this time; then may I crave leave to creepe in amongst the crowd without preſumption, in this abyſſe of troubles, with my preſent (to this great work in hand for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation) compoſed of naked truth clad in her owne colours, in a few ſuccinct Arguments, cloſely backing one another, as lincks in a chaine, drawing all one way in one ſtrong cord, not one of which I conceive could be wanting, though I have ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died as much brevity as might ſtand with perſpicuitie, in abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe ſo very weighty, as to give vigour and life to the active axiome of the time, and preſent exigent, for the finall extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the uſurped duplicated authoritie of the Prelacy; the great boll or branch of the Romiſh Hierarchy: Eclipſing all our glory, cluding all Authoritie, by their lofty dignitie and innate Antipathy to all true Church policy, and our Parliamentary ſublyme authoritie, and noble deſignes, to which above all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſervice I profeſſe to be devoted, and to which I here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent my homage and hoſtage of my beſt endeavours. If herein thou findeſt any thing worthy of obſervance, uſe it to thine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage for the common good.</p>
            <p>Every one within his limits improving his endeavours and intereſt in this preſent honourable Parliament, to make the Hydraes head of Prelacy, with all the corrupt members of that
<pb facs="tcp:93696:3"/>body, the holocauſt to expiate the wrath of God ſo long threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt this Land defiled with their abhominations, and bloody cruelties, in their long oppoſition of Chriſts Kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and that by an Antichriſtian tyrannicall government, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with all Chriſtian policy and free ſubjects liberties, the vindicating whereof ſhall aſſuredly adde more luſtre to this ancient Kingdomes glory, and our Parliaments deſerved fame, than all the gemmes or radiant ſtones in the Triple crowne or Spaniſh Diadem.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Prelates of late have been ſo preſumptuouſly buſie in melting baſe mettall, and caſting their Canons, and mounting them ſo high as to batter down all Religion, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, fortifying their tottering holds of Epiſcopacy in the rearing againe the old ruines of Babell. Shall not the Lords ſervants be much more bold for Chriſt, than they for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? ſhall they fortifie and plant Canons contrary to both Lawes of God and of the Land, to batter downe our Religion and liberties, and ſhall not we reare our forts and plant Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of proofe by both Lawes, and play upon their Babell Building? long agoe, yea of old determined to deſtruction, as <hi>Jericho,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 6.</note> and curſed they who ſhall attempt to reare its ruines againe.</p>
            <p>If ever were a time for Chriſts ſervants, as men of another ſpirit, to take courage and Camp about Babell; then now when ſhe hath laid our Zion waſte: high time for every faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God, and loyall ſubject to be up and be doing, every one ſomething within compaſſe of his calling. This is ſolely the Authors minde and ayme at this time in Conſcience of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, here repreſenting to thy view, a new reard battery againſt Babells loftie fort of Prelacy, planted with ten new caſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of old tryed mettall, playing upon their tottering building on all parts, from the higheſt pinacle to the ground-work and foundation: which is not onely ſandy but laid in a filthy dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, and waſting daily; ſo the ſervants of Chriſt may even hence be encouraged, that the downfall of it is feizible enough if they campe about it with courage and conſtancy, as the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites about Jericho, and we ſhall ſee it fall ſuddenly with Shout and Cry.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93696:4"/>
            <list>
               <head>The names of the Canons, and how they are planted and diſcharged.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>Canon ab alto fulminans,</hi> ſtrikes downe right from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven fiery hot thunderbolts at their two high pinacles of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopall bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phemy.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>Canon lucis a meridie fulgens,</hi> payes them on the blinde ſide for they look South-eaſt, Rome-ward, and are blinde South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Sun-ward; their right eye is darkned and no light in them, <hi>Zach. 14.17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Canon Regis Caroli Chriſti vindex,</hi> playes upon the corner ſtone of their building.</item>
               <item>4 <hi>Canon John the Baptiſt ex officio ſuo,</hi> playes upon their breaſt-works.</item>
               <item>5 <hi>Canon old Romane on the South-eaſt, which way they look moſt for help,</hi> playes upon the maine bulk and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of their building, where all their treaſure and baggage lyes.</item>
               <item>6 <hi>Canon Apoſtolick,</hi> in a running trench, cloſely batters the foundation round about on every ſide.</item>
               <item>7 <hi>Canon ex ore Chriſti eradicans,</hi> or Canon roote all, fires a myne which ſprings and ſcatters the ground-ſtones of the foundation.</item>
               <item>8 <hi>Canon gregis &amp; utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> legis,</hi> or Canon clenſe all, from the honourable high Court of Parliament, runs round about their works, charged with great and ſmall ſhort, ſweeping out root and branches, and clenſing the Land of all their remnants.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The next two Canons are planted upon their paſſage to cut off all ayde and ſuccour from them, whiles the other are battering.</head>
               <item>9 <hi>Canon Minans,</hi> or ſtand of Aſſiſtants.</item>
               <item>10 <hi>Canon flagrans,</hi> a long Baſiliske whoſe ſiery eyes at long diſtance threatens death and deſtruction to all that come neare to plead for them, or partake with them against the Lord Ieſus, the mighty King incenſed to wrath againſt their working.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:93696:4"/>
            <p>And thus courteous Reader, if thou mindeſt aright this ſervice, I hope thou ſhalt finde it not unprofitable at this time, but affording ſome uſefull inſtructions to all ſorts of men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by tis hoped ſome may be bettered in ſome meaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1.</hi> The firſt to be looked at are the ſuffering ſervants of God, who have lyen under long and great oppreſſions under the Prelates, theſe may hence be comforted, to ſee their long deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cauſe at length victorious, though the ſeidge prove long, theſe Canons are ſtrong, will not miſcarry if the ſervice be hot, nay if ſome of them be not diſcharged at all that depend on mens hands and handling, yet there are enough beſides in the number that will not ſpare them, and are in the divine hand of a jealous God, who will let flie at them, one thunderclap from on high at their blaſphemy, will teare their building from top to bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, or a word from the Lord Ieſus mouth, ſhall roote them when he begins to roare in mount Zion, his voice is powerfull and full of majeſtie, <hi>Pſal. 29.4.</hi> he will ſhake their deepe roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and lay them on the ground; his eyes are as flames of fire if once his wrath begin to burne, woe to them he finds in his way of advancing his kingdome; he will make waste mountains and hills of greateſt enemies, for the Lord is jealous, the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeth, the Lord avengeth and is furious, the Lord will take vengeance on his enemies, <hi>Nahum 1.2.</hi> and he will comfort Zion, and build her waſte places, he hath had reſpect to the prayer of the deſolate, and will not tarry, they may then be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, to them belongs the ſongs and palms of victory over the beaſt of Rome and his Image, in theſe bratts of Babell; theſe are they that come out of great tribulation, that keepe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and faith of Jeſus, that are not defiled with the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of the whoriſh woman, for they are the virgins that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lambe, and ſhall enter with him through the gates in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Citie. The conſideration whereof ſhould mitigate their preſent ſorrowes, having an eye to the recompence of reward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2.</hi> The enemies of Chriſts kingdome may read their doome from the righteous judgement of the Lord of hoaſts, and be at laſt provoked to repentance and reſignation of their unlawfull offices, and doe homage to Chriſts Scepter, who otherwiſe will come as a theſe in the night upon them, and cut off their pompe
<pb facs="tcp:93696:5"/>and power, and make them naked and unarmed, and cast them out as dogs out of the holy Citie; and ſo there be left them no place to repentance, though they ſeek it with teares, out of time, when the gate of the Kingdome is ſhut againſt them, they may howle, and cry, and knock till they be weary, ere S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> keyes come to open. This will certainly befall them ſooner or later, if they repent not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3.</hi> Thoſe that are gone back to the fleſh-pots of Egypt, and are ſwimming downe with the ſtreame of the time, may be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned to returne, and come out of the tents of theſe wicked men, leaſt by partaking in their ſinnes, they partake of their plagues;
<note place="margin">Iſa.</note> for it is the time of the Lords vengeance, the yeare of recompence of the Controverſies of Zion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4.</hi> All ſorts of men, loyall ſubjects of the King, and good Patriots of their Countrey, may be moved with pitty to helpe to remove the inſupportable burthens which preſſe downe the land to ruine and miſery,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi dolor ibi digitus,</hi> is the part and dutie of every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> all flowing from the Hierarchy: and till the preſſures in Religion be removed, and Chriſts kingdome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, the Common-weale cannot be eaſed: they are like <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> twinns, they mourne and rejoyce, live and dye toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Tis the office of Prelacy that keepes out Christs kingly office, is the <hi>Achan</hi> ſin that troubles the Land, and is the cauſe of all our miſeries, and threatens ſtill greater: if that be not removed, Gods wrath will not be appeaſed, our troubles not ended. The Lord pitty us, and eaſe himſelfe and us of theſe his Adverſaries, who will not have Chriſt to reigne over them.</p>
            <p>Undi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> concurrunt ac creſcit turba malorum, ſed cum probroſi caſtra ſuperba tenent.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Lament. 5.17, 18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For this our heart is faint, our eyes are dimme, becauſe of the mountaine of Zion which is deſolate, the Foxes walke upon it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93696:5"/>
            <head>SOME ARGVMENTS AND MOTIVES TO The finall Extirpation of the uſurped unlawfull Government of the HIERARCHY. <hi>AS</hi> Having no foundation in the Scriptures, but meerly in that filthy dunghill the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law of the Popes Authoritie, and therefore Antichriſtian.</head>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> I.</head>
               <p>THat Name which is onely proper to the Lord Jeſus, is unlawfull, yea blaſphemy for any man to aſſume. But ſo is the name Archbiſhop onely proper to the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.31.) the chiefe Shepheard and Biſhop of our ſoules. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Ergo</hi> for any man to aſſume that name is unlawfull; yea blaſphemy, and the blaſphemer ſhould be ſtoned to death, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.11.14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>That office whoſe originall is not knowne is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93696:6"/>But the originall of the office of Archbiſhop is not knowne: as the chiefe champion of Prelacy confeſſeth, <hi>Whitgift cont. Cartwright, pag.</hi> 351. And further, nothing can be ſaid for the primacy of a Metropolitane Biſhop, but what will as well maintaine the primacy of the Pope as univerſall Biſhop of all the world. <hi>Ergo</hi> the office of an Archbiſhop is unlawfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>That name and office which is unlawſull, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my for any man to aſſume, no Prince or humane power may lawfully give. But ſo is the name and office of Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, as before. <hi>Ergo</hi> no Prince or humane power may lawfully give it to any man; and wee hope his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty when he is rightly informed, will explode the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of it: this is the very corner ſtone of their building, if this once faile, the whole fabricke will ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly tumble upon their heads. The Lord grant it, and put into the heart of our royall Soveraigne to execute his will upon theſe Bratts of <hi>Babell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>No officer in the Church is lawfull, who cannot prove his function from the word, as <hi>Iohn</hi> did when the Prieſts queſtioned him, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.23.25. But all theſe officers in the Hierarchy from the chiefe Metropolitane to the meaneſt Apparitour, are ſuch as cannot prove their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from the word when they are queſtioned: their onely prooſes are fulminations of Canons, cenſures, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications, priſons, and fines, cutting of cares and noſes and brands. <hi>Ergo</hi> unlawfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>Thoſe officers whoſe names, offices, and practiſes are deriyed from Antichriſt, and ſerve principally to uphold
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93696:6"/>and propagate his Kingdome, ought not to governe the Church the Spouſe of Chriſt: who will not have her ruled by ſuch as live by the vices of men, and hyre of whores, commutations of pennance, ſelling of ſins and giving libertie to all licentiouſneſſe. But Archbiſhops, Dioceſan Biſhops, Deanes Archdeacons, Chancellours, Officialls, &amp;c. their names offices and practiſes are ſuch; as in one word appeares in that they have their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that filthy dunghill of the Canon law, and thence their practiſes, <hi>Ex mero officio,</hi> are onely warranted to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and propagate the Kingdome of Antichriſt, and bring in Popery againe. Neither can any thing be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for a Dioceſan Biſhop and Church, but from the ſame ground will ariſe an Univerſall Church and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, they ſtand upon one Antichriſtian foundation, which makes the Prelates and their officers love the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſo well. <hi>Ergo</hi> they ought not to governe the Church the Spouſe of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>Thoſe officers in the Church, whoſe offices and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment from the foundation and very nature of their offices, doe waſte and overthrow the principall functions of the Church and offices of Chriſt, are not of Chriſt but of Antichriſt. But ſuch are the offices of Archbiſhops, Dioceſan Biſhops, &amp;c. and the reſt of that rable. <hi>Ergo</hi> not of Chriſt but of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>The Major I ſuppoſe no ſound Proteſtant will deny.</p>
               <p>The Minor propoſition is that muſt abide all the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery from the lofty Prelacy, their forts and mounts of molehill-authoritie; but in the skirmiſh, we ſhall finde them all in a confuſion, flouriſhing their colours, and drawing forth and mounting their Canons, and playing and diſcharging upon their own Canon Law, as if they ſeemed to batter their owne foundation, (like cunning Fencers that make a flouriſh on the ſtage and ſeeme to knocke downe one another, but 'tis a point of art to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93696:7"/>maintaine the trade) but as ſoone as the fury is over, we ſhall finde them with their Canons drawne into their old fortification, and upon the next advantage in the field againe, and at their old work and battery, at the foundations of the Church with greater fury, (it being the very nature of their office ſo to doe) yea (if God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent not now by the diligent hand of this honourable Parliament) to mount their Canons and Canon Law to ſuch a height, as to batter at the Royall Authoritie, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary priviledges, and Subjects liberties, to make havock of all, and bring in and erect a papall forreigne Juriſdiction in this Land againe.</p>
               <p>There be two maine Branches of our Minor propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">Two branches of the Minor.</note> that the offices and government of the Hierarchy, 1. from the foundation of, 2. from the very nature of their offices and government doe waſte and overthrow the functions of the Church and offices of Chriſt, we will demonſtrate.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">Firſt branch.</note> That it is founded in the Canon Law, what their offices are, and how to be exerciſed, in ſuch practices as uphold and propagate the Kingdome of Antichriſt, read <hi>Angelus de Clanſio,</hi> and other Canoniſts, where you may ſee their warrant for their offices, and practices in their government: to which upon all occaſions they have their recourſe in any difficultie, and fetch their dark light in ſtead of the Scriptures. So as when a new Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, a new Archdeacon, or a new Chancellour comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his new office like a freſh man, the inferiour officers that be old practicioners in that Law, muſt inſtruct him in any matter of difficulty falling out in his government, after that Law, by which all muſt be ordered: and that it is true that the Canon Law is the foundation of their offices and government. See a book compiled out of the Canon Law, and entituled; <hi>Reformatio Legum Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticarum,</hi> Printed 1571, and now of late reprinted and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Authoritie; and in he Preface of the ſaid book it is confeſſed, that the Canon Law of Popiſh govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſtill retained in <hi>England</hi> to that day, and ſo is to this.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93696:7"/>
               <p>Now what this Canon Law is, appeares by the Law it ſelfe to be nothing elſe but the Lawes and Decrees of the Popes of Rome and their authoritie point blanck oppoſite to the Lawes of God in generall, and the Lawes of Chriſt (for governing his Church) in ſpeciall, and to our Kings prerogative royall and lawes of the Land. And 'tis a wonder how this Canon Law, branded and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed by ſo many Statutes and Acts of Parliament, ſhould be ſuffered to be exerciſed in this Land without (as Lawyers ſay) the incutring of a <hi>Praemunire.</hi> being a Law of forreigne and Papall Juriſdiction, aboliſhed by the Stat. of 4. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.23. and others. And how this uſurped govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is growne to an inſufferable height, overtopping all authoritie, religion and liberties, I leave to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Lawes, and grave judgements of this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Parliament.</p>
               <p>We come then to the ſecond branch of our propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that it is from the very nature of their offices,
<note place="margin">Second branch.</note> that they waſte and overthrow the ſunctions of the Church and offices of Chriſt, meerly from that their foundation and warrant (in the Canon Law) of their practices in all they doe in their offices, as before.</p>
               <p>Now the nature of every thing is beſt tryed and ſeene in the things which iſſue from it, as the proper works and actions of every function, ſpringing from the roote and foundation, as giving Lawes for warrant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, ſo vigour and life for execution; and from thence we ſhall ſee as in a Proſpect through their practices (ſo warranted) into the nature of their offices, and whether they waſte the Church and overthrow the offices of Chriſt or no.</p>
               <p>The principail ſunctions of the Church are; 1.
<note place="margin">Foure maine functions of the Church.</note> the word. 2. prayer. 3. Sacraments. 4. diſcipline; all which like the mother that old withered wrinckled faced whore of Rome, they have moſt foully adulterated and filthily polluted.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the word 'tis the very nature of their offices,
<note place="margin">1 The World.</note>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93696:8"/>flowing in through their ſo warranted practices, to mix and mingle it with mens inventions, and ſhut their eyes againſt the Scriptures brightneſſe; tell one of theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of warrant from the word, and he will give you ſuch a learned anſwer, as would make his horſe breake his halter, if he knew how unmercifull his Maſter were to his beaſt, as to queſtion what warrant he hath from the word to give him a peck of Oats. An argument from Scripture ſets them all in a rage; ſuch an antipathy there is between the word and the very nature of their offices. 2. They corrupt the word with falſe doctrines, from their Canons, Books of Articles and Homilies, writings and preachings, wherewith the Pulpits ſound alowd throughout the Land. 3. Their offices are to cauſe the people drinke theſe troubled waters, or drive their backs to the wall. 4. They have turned the Miniſtery wholly into a Jewiſh-Popiſh Sacrificing Prieſthood. 5. They ſet up a new kinde of reading-preaching, and ſuppreſſe ſound preaching, ſilence and ſuſpend the orthodox Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and fill their places with Metaphyſicall cloudy-brain'd Humaniſts, Arminian
<note place="margin">* Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bancks.</note> and Popiſh fellowes, who uſually ſtuffe their Sermons out of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicks, and the Fryars Poſtills. 6. In ſtead of the word they ſet up Images, Crucifixes, Altats, and teaching Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, to ſtirre up the dull minds of men, againſt Chriſts prerogative and propheticall office, to which it belongs to teach his Church by his word and works, and not by mens inventions and works of mens hands. 7. They Pope-like corrupt the word with their ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing breath, breathing forth for Scripture what they pleaſe, ſome are the Fathers, others the ſonnes of the Church, and <hi>in ſumma</hi> the Church of themſelves, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt themſelves above the Scriptures, eſpecially when they meet in the Convocation houſe, and have their Canons in caſting, they make lawes above and againſt the word, and preach for them, &amp; puniſh the breach of them more than the breach of Gods Commandements. 8. By ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their offices they aſſume a power to conferre holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93696:8"/>upon things and places, conſecrate Churches, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and places, and place holineſſe in their ſuperſtitions and abhominations, as Altars, Altar-cringing, Jeſus, and Eaſt-worſhipping, &amp;c. Whereas the word alone hath power to ſanctifie and make holy. Thus by bringing in the accurſed thing of Romes Idolatry, they are become the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bans</hi> that trouble the Land. 8. Nature works ſo ſtrongly in their offices, as you may now ſee it in their bold impudent faces, profeſſing reconciliation of us to Rome, pronouncing them happy that ſhall be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to reconcile the petty ſeeming differences, and make us at one with their mother, but I hope before that be done they and their mother ſhall be both confounded, <hi>Jere.</hi> 50.11, 12. For the light hath dazled them, the Sunne is gone downe, and the day is dark over them to make them confounded and aſhamed, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.17. <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.6, 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For Prayer,
<note place="margin">2 Prayer.</note> how doe they by their very office profeſſe and practice the corrupting of it, which as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe ſhould be purely offred, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. They, 1. fill the houſe of God with ſmoke of the ſtrange fire of their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations of all ſorts, new and old inventions, Letany and long ſom ſervice, ſaid and ſung, with yelling and chanting like the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> their old and new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, fopperies, ſecond Service, and corrupt prayers, all put together, as like the Maſſe as an apple is like an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renge. 2. By their offices, they ordaine Prieſts of the loweſt of the people, to offer up their corrupt prayers, as dunibe Sir <hi>Iohns,</hi> ale-houſe-keepers, and generally vile perſons, who like <hi>Elyes</hi> ſonnes cauſe men to abhorre their offerings. 3. All this corruption in worſhip flowes out of the Canon Law, as the filthy fountaine through their offices, as the pipes to ſet it abroad to infect the world, and is preſerved as in ciſternes in the Canons and ſervice-booke, the ſecond maine baſis whereupon Epiſcopacy ſtands in the dunghill Canon Law, which caſts ſuch a foule ſavour in the noſthrills of God, as we may admire his patience in ſuffering it ſo long, without ſweeping it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93696:9"/>and us all together away in ſome ſtrange inundation of Judgement.</p>
               <p>Nothing but a flood of Juſtice and reformation will prevent his kindled anger againſt us, manifeſted of late in ſo many fearefull and prodigious ſignes and wonders, eſpecially in and about Churches, as if he had pointed with his finger that there is his quarrell, one ſtrange fire procuring another, and threatning yet greater if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not, reforme not.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3 Sacraments.</note> For the Sacraments, how have they changed them into Sacrifices, witneſſe their baptiſmall regeneration, kneeling at Sacrament, or bread-worſhip, wherein wee are beholding to <hi>Coſterus</hi> the Jeſuite for telling us their meaning right out, if Chriſt (ſaith he) were not teally in the bread, our kneeling were worſe and more groſſe Idolatry than that of the Heathen. Thus they turne the Sacraments into propitiatory Sacrifices, to waſh away ſinne and conferre grace, <hi>xapere op rato:</hi> and ſo the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward work of Gods Spurit baniſhed, it would be too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to be more in particulars.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">4 Diſcipline.</note> For diſcipline, the nature of the office ſhews it ſelfe here moſt, as in the ſtrongeſt pulſe, working with all its might continually by their Canons and Canon Law au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to oppoſe and ſuppreſſe Chriſts Kingly office and government, to repaire and reſtore the ruinous king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichriſt, and that <hi>Iudas</hi>-like, <hi>Antichriſt</hi>-like under a feigned profeſſion of friendſhip to Chriſt. 2. Their offices uphold the Popiſh Canon law govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which hath left us no footſteps of the Apoſtolike diſcipline, and kingly office of Chriſt, wholly ſwept away in the great deluge of Popery, and never yet reſtored as our firſt reformers aymed, which may appeare by the Preface to the commination in the common prayer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke, and were enough to ſet all reformed Spirits on work to perfect what they in the infancy of reformation left undone or ſaw not clearly, being then newly riſen out of the long darkſome night of Popery, and how ſhould their diligence ſhame our negligence in ſo bright
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93696:9"/>a Sun-ſhine of the Goſpel as we have had ſince, and ſtirre up our ſpirits to ſearch out and ſet up that primitive diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline they aymed at now above fourſcore yeares agoe, which hath been ſo much diſputed for, written for, and petitioned for at ſo many Parliaments, and been onely hundred by theſe Antichriſtian Prelates, whoſe office it is to juſtle Chriſt from his throne, untill the words of God be fulfilled
<note place="margin">* Apoc. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>, becauſe they know the ſetting up of his kingdome will be the downfall of theirs, they cannot ſtand together; therefore this hath been long their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-peice, with all their craft and cunning to uphold their Papall government and tyranny by their Canons and Canon law, to cruſh all who have ſtood in their way to oppoſe them, and plead for Chriſts owne diſcipline, uſing them worſe than Turkes would have done as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the multitude of Miniſters and people in priſons murthered, of thouſands baniſhed, of families ſcattered, and eſtates ruined for ſtanding for Chriſts diſcipline. 2. The very nature of their office is to thirſt after the blood of Gods ſervants; <hi>Where Antipas my faithfull mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr is ſlaine, there is Sathans throne, Apoc.</hi> 2.13. Of this tyranny let one of themſelves be witneſſe, (out of whoſe mouth the Lord exacted this teſtimony) Prelate <hi>Vaughan</hi> in a ſpeech to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Morton</hi> long agoe, (now Prelate of <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſme</hi>) confeſſed that the perſecution of theſe times were worſe than in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, and gave reaſons for it. Now let Prelate <hi>Morton</hi> ſpeak how they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in his time and by him, or if he will not, it may be God may exact it of him ſometime with more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of conſcience than any of his predeceſſors, becauſe he ſins againſt greater light and more warnings; yea let Prelate <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> ſpeak whether his hands be cleare of the bloody perſecutions in <hi>Ireland</hi> of late, and if they will not, the earth ſhall diſcover her blood, and no more hide her ſlaine: the infection of the bloody office is growne to ſuch a height as hath not left any one of them untain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one way or other. 4. If they all ſhould hold their peace, the ſtones will cry in their High Commiſſions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93696:10"/>and Courts, their books and Court Records ſhall teſtifie to poſterity of their tyranny in government. So as it hath been an old tryed Maxime of their Courts; <hi>That a good man makes a bad cauſe there:</hi> how hath the terrour of their Courts made many Miniſters and people, like the figge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, caſt their fruit before they felt the ſtorme, upon the firſt puffe of winde of appearance of troubles, when they have heard an I ſeene how other men have been cruſhed and undone by them
<note place="margin">* Veſtigia ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</note>. The very ſight of a Puritane (as they brand them in their Courts, makes their blood riſe and their ſpirits rage and ſwell as againſt the mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of their Dominion. And if the Papiſts plot of a long intended bloody Maſſacre had prevailed and not of late from Heaven been prevented, I beleeve their white ſleeves would have been dyed in our blood ere now: their dog-like appetite ſo hungers after the Puritanes blood, as the very nature of their office ſo to doe, and cannot be otherwiſe, for this is the fruit of the old withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſtock of Romes Hierarchy, and the longer this tree of Prelacy ſpringing out of that root ſhall ſtand, it grows taller and ſtronger, from the nouriſhment it receives from the ſap and root in the dunghill foundation of the Canon Law: and according to the nature of the ſoyle the fruit muſt be, and ſo of neceſſitie bring forth daily more bitter fruits to the Church of God, like apples of <hi>Sodome.</hi> 5. The brightneſſe of divine truth in this point of diſcipline, hath ſo dazled the Prelaticall partie, that of late they have confeſſed the diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be the ſame with the Church of Rome; and yet they are either ſo modeſt as aſhamed to have it called Antichriſtian, or els ſo impudent as to deny the Pope to be Antichriſt; as whores and bawds love the gaine aſid pleaſarcof their filthy trade, but cannot endure the name. What a ſhame is it to our Religion and Nation, to uphold Artichriſts filthy trade and government, the mother of all abhominations, and miſtreſſe of whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; a thing ſo ſcandalous to all the reformed world of Proteſtants. 6. Let our deare friends and exiles in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93696:10"/>ſpeake, and the whole Kingdome at home of the ſcattered families of Chriſts ſervants, witneſſe what ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock they have made of the Church; and what rule they keep in Court and Countrey, Towne and Citie, from the Metropolitane to the meaneſt ſon of the Church, how they pierck and pranſe it, above all Nobilitie and Centry, and become the onely brave fellows and <hi>fac t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ums,</hi> in all affaires in the Common-weale as well as in the Church. So as at length they have over-ſhadowed the whole State, Eclipſed the very royall Authoritie, hindred the Sun-ſhine of his Princely aſpect from his loyall ſubjects, and which is not the leaſt of all, by the miſts of then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions and ſmoak of their ſuperſtitious abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ariſing out of their ſulphurious Seas, like the Aſphal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, they darken the light of the ſun of Righteouſneſſe, and hinder us of the Lord Jeſus his beautifull and ſhining rayes and influence of his ſweet countenance, which like the Sun in his ſtrength, would revive all our droopings, and make the Land to flouriſh, when once his throne, his reſt were ſet up amongſt us. O how would he make his reſt glorious, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.10.</p>
               <p>Thus at laſt to conclude this argument, we have found in the office of Prelacy, the principall markes of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; corrupt doctrine, corrupt worſhip and tyranny in government; all naturally flowing through their offices out of the ſame dunghill foundation with Antichriſt; for if it were not in the nature and power of their offices thus to doe, their kingdome would long agoe have falne and come to nothing.</p>
               <p>And therefore the Prelates are wrongfully blamed for abuſing their offices, thevery nature and right uſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is to waſt and overthrow the Church and offices of Chriſt, to overturne Kingdomes and Lawes, to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the kingdome of Antichriſt; the office is ſo bad they cannot uſe it otherwiſe, no more than one of them can ride a horſe blind and lame of all leggs, over mountaines and hills, without hazard of his neck: the office or Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy is the blind and lame Jade which they are moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93696:11"/>upon to over-ride all divine and humane authoritie, and will certainly breake their necks ere long; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beſt office their friends can doe them, is to ſtop their gallopping, and to ſave their necks helpe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> This cannot be ſo, will ſome ſay, why ſhould the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates be ſo venturous, or ride ſo madly, they ſure have a more care of themſelves, than ſo deſperately precipitate themſelves to fatall ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ </seg>
                  </label> Becauſe they ride for a better horſe, whence they had this, which makes them ſo loath to part with the Jade, and rather will venture a fall: every Prieſt rides for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, every perſon for a Prebendary, every Prebend for a Deanery, ſo for a Biſhoprick, an Archbiſhoprick, a Cardinallſhip, till ſome of them that ride faſteſt at laſt be mounted on mens ſhoulders, to make Princes run at their ſtirrup. Complaine not then of the Prelates abuſe of their offices in trampling upon you, when it is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the beaſt, and ride he muſt: if you would be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of your paine, diſmount the rider, and knock the lame Jade on the head.</p>
               <p>And thus we ſee how under a pretence of love to Chriſt, they overthrow all his offices, as Prophet, Prieſt, and King, and therefore the concluſion ſtands firme, that they are not of Chriſt, but of Antichriſt: and then our next Argument tells us what will be the end of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every plant which my heavenly Father hath not planted, ſhall be rooted out,</hi> Mat. 15.13. The Prelacy and their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices are no plants of the Fathers planting. <hi>Ergo</hi> they ſhall be rooted out, and as an abhominable branch (of the old withered ſtock of Romes Hierarchy be cut downe and caſt out of the Church) as the garments of the ſlaine, (thruſt through with the ſword of authoritie) and as a carcaſſe trod under foote, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.19.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93696:11"/>
               <p>The Major propoſition is undeniable, being out of his mouth who is faithfull and true, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13.14. and will make it good in his own time, for out of his mouth goes a two edged ſword, the ſword of his Spirit, ſharpening and thruſting forth the ſword of the Magiſtrate, which in due time he will cauſe to be forbiſhed and made bright to the ſlaughter of theſe his enemies, who will not have him to rule over them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.17.</p>
               <p>The Minor is their part to prove. See Argument 4. And if they have any Letters Patents for their offices, let them open their black boxes and produce them, or els as polluted be put from the Prieſthood, as thoſe, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7.64. that could not reckon up their Genealogie from <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi.</hi> 2. In all the book of God from the beginning of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis</hi> to the end of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> we find not one word of warrant for the name or office of an Archbiſhop, Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Biſhop, Deane, Archdeacon. Chancellour, or any of their orders, but are meerly derived from Antichriſt, crept into the Church by carnall policy and flattery, and abuſe of Princes favours, and have no foundation but in the Canon Law of the Pope, as before, <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. and 6. thats all the divine authoritie they have, and no wonder if it be divine enough for them to ſtand upon, being the ſame with Antichriſt; for Dioceſan Biſhops were the firſt ſtep whereby the Papacy mounted to its height, and are the pillars of its ſupport even to this day. But when the Prelates father their authoritie, ſome upon God the Father, ſome upon God the Sonne, and others upon the holy Ghoſt, they declare themſelves to be of that ſtamp Chriſt reproves and accuſes of blaſphemy, and to be of the Synagogue of Sathan, who ſay they are Jewes and are not but doe lye, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.9. Who ſay they are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and are not, but are found lyers, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.2. So then when they boaſt of divine authoritie, they are right like themſelves, for that is another mark of Antichriſt, the adding of lyes to all their abhominations, for which they ſhall be caſt out of the holy Citie, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The whole ſtreame of truth flowing out of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93696:12"/>Scriptures, as the fountain runs ſo ſtrongly againſt them that down they goe to the Sea of Rome, that dead Sea, to fetch their pedigree from that ancient family of long Enmitie to Chriſt, the Ancient of dayes, and fountaine of all Antiquitie, before whom nothing was, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom nothing was made or done, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.2, 3.</p>
               <p>That this is ſo, ſee clearly M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul Baine</hi> his dioceſan tryall, the very Prelates rats-bane, and will burſt them ere long; it ſavours ſo ſweetly of the Scriptures fragrant fulneſſe and excellency by the breathings of Gods Spirit (which is the Prelates deadly poyſon) that none of them durſt ever take it in hand to anſwer it, now about twenty years publiſhed; and there who will may read the doome of their divine authoritie.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If they flie to Antiquitie, we anſ. 1. We acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no antiquitie, but what is according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Judge of all Controverſie; its a ſure rule of the learned againſt the Papiſts, that <hi>Whatſoever is not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word, but by or beſides the Word is againſt the Word.</hi> 2. We anſwer with <hi>Cyprian</hi> the flowre and ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt bloome of all antiquitie, a Martyr and a Biſhop, but no Lord, or Dioceſan Biſhop. <hi>Epiſt. ad Pomp. Epist.</hi> 74. Antiquitie without truth, is antiquitie of errour, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie without truth is nothing worth ſaith our learned <hi>Whitakers, Controverſe de Eccleſ. quaeſt.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>But to leave them more without excuſe, we wil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute yet one tryall more of them, which we learne from our great Maſter the Lord Jeſus, for the diſcovery of falſe Prophets, who come in ſheepes cloathing, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, are avening Wolves, <hi>By their fruits yee ſhal know them,</hi> Mat. 7.15, 16, 20. Falſe Prophets in Scripture al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſet forth ſuch as have no lawfull but a pretended office, ſo the Dioceſan Biſhops, &amp;c. are the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets wee have to doe withall; the name of Prophets, ſo the name of Biſhops is the ſheeps cloathing they come in to doe the works of Sathan and Antichriſt; the very name of Biſhop (which in it ſelfe is good) is like <hi>Jacobs</hi> voice with <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands, theres much power of Sathan
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93696:12"/>uſed under the ſhelter of words and names, as of great force to deceive, Mountebanck-like, and therefore ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luther. de fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo nom. &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 330.</note> they ſhew or ſet out themſelves as if they were Paſtours of the Church, as if they were Biſhops, when they are meere ſhadowes, ſacrificing perſons, dumb ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and painted truncks, under the loftie high title of Biſhops, deſtroying the whole world: and therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been too long deceived with words and names, wee now will follow Chriſts rule, <hi>By their fruits to know them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The office of Prelacy, is the lame Jade we ſpoke of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now, and hath been long tryed by the Word, but now is growne ſo hot ridden, as will not abide that kinde of handling, therefore the laſt tryall of them is this, <hi>By their fruits to know them,</hi> and ſo by their footſteps we ſhall ſee which way they are running.</p>
               <p>Now the fruits of the office, wee have ſhewed in the foregoing Argument to be the overthrowing of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Chriſt, and propagating the Kingdome of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, <hi>Ex mero officio,</hi> as the proper fruits of their functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and naturally flowing through the office out of that filthy lake of Romes authoritie (as before) and therefore the fruits muſt needs be according to the ſoyle, bitter fruits to the Church of God. And here wee will take a further tryall of them, and how they grow and increaſe in fruitfulneſſe.</p>
               <p>Such plants as are of the Fathers planting, the Son purgeth that they may bring forth more fruit, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Fruits unto holineſſe:</hi> Epheſ. 4.24. But we ſee when theſe men once enter into a Biſhops Sea, or other their offices, they ſoone wither and caſt their fruit; how many of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and good abilities, before they entred into theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt offices, have quickly after fallen under the withering curſe of the Fig-tree, <hi>Never fruit grew more upon thee.</hi> And how can it be otherwiſe, theres ſuch a plaguy infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction lyes in the office ariſing out of the filthy dunghill foundation, which rots and blaſts all the fruits of their learning and morall parts, and renders them wholly like
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93696:13"/>the ſoyle they live in, and corrupt ayre of the Epiſcopall Seas they breath in: heres the infection, the poyſon that kills them ſooner or later; tis in the office, not ſo much in the perſon, but as the office infects him; therefore no ſafetie to their perſons till they be put out of the infected places to lodge in freſh ayre.
<note place="margin">A Caveat.</note> Their counſell then is not good who would onely remove and change the perſons, and put other learned men in the places. O it is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt cruelty you can doe to theſe mens ſoules, you had better place them to live in a Peſt-houſe, or caſt their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies alive into the <hi>Mari Mortuo,</hi> than into a Biſhops Sea, if they be good men they ſhould ſo ſave their ſoules, whereas this way you hazard their ſoules and bodies both. Let none then be ſo cruell to their friends, to put them upon this preferment on ſo deſperate a condition, wherein its as poſſible for them to bring forth good fruit as for an Apricock to grow in a dunghill. Wee have Chriſts aſſurance for it, <hi>A corrupt tree cannot bring forth good fruit;</hi> the tree ſtill ſignifies the office not the perſon, for its ſpoken of falſe Prophets, and tryall of them by their fruits; <hi>Doe men gather grapes on thornes, or figges on thiſtles,</hi> ſtill ſhewes it to be the office of thoſe falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, where Chriſt never ordained any good fruits to grow, and therefore none to be expected, but of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt tree corrupt fruit; <hi>Therefore every tree which brings not forth good fruit, ſhall be hewen downe and caſt into the fire,</hi> Mat. 7.16. to 20. This good fruit as wee ſhewed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now is <hi>fruit unto holineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We will try then the fruits of this tree of Epiſcopacy, and the ſeverall branches of its offices, and we finde them all taſte of the dunghill ſoyle, they are rooted in and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their proper nouriſhment from, and are no <hi>fruite unto holineſſe:</hi> For wee doe finde by wofull experience, that the fruits of their offices and government hath filled the Land with all prophaneneſſe, and ſinning with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe in all licentiouſneſſe, and therefore unholy offices, an unholy government, which not onely countenance ſincks of ſin and wickedneſſe, but live in and are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93696:13"/>by the vices of men, as the hire of whores, ſelling of ſinnes and filthineſſe, commutations of pennance, and oppreſſions of his Majeſties Subjects, and diſabling them for King and Countryes ſervice. This is the chiefe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of their offices, which if once, with the Canon Law that warrants theſe practices, were taken away, we ſhould quickly ſee this great Amphitheater of Prelacy moulder downe and fall into the dunghill from whence it aroſe, and then one faire flood of Juſtice from this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Parliament, would ſoone ſweep away all the filth together, and clenſe the Land of theſe corrupt and contagious offices.</p>
               <p>The ſeats of their offices, their Cathedrall Cities and Pallaces are very donnes of all filthineſſe and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the moſt uncleane birds in the Countrey reſort to dwell under their ſhadow, as having there libertie to live in all licentiouſneſſe. The name of <hi>holineſſe</hi> there, is as a Jew to an Egyptian an abhomination; their Abbeyes, Deaneries and Epiſcopall Seas are like the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phaltites,</hi> pitchy ſulphurious Lake, nothing that favours of or breaths holineſſe can live there. Their Courts and Judgements-ſeats are ſo many batteryes againſt holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, thundering and flaming out fire and ſmoke from their Canons and murthering pieces, at the very name of (or perſons that looke after) holineſſe, as the mortall enemies of their dominion and government, againſt which if a man let the leaſt word fall, preſently <hi>ex officio</hi> excommunicate him, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> ere he ſtirre from them, he ſhall not have a warning peace to be gone, but a whole battery of Canons diſcharged upon him, in ſuch heate and rage, fire and ſmoke of their fulminations, as he ſhall ſcarce know what ground he ſtands on, till for change of ayre he be hald away to a ſtincking priſon, to complaine to the bare-walls. Oh if he be a Puritane, thats condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the abſtract, enough to rid the Land of him, yea the world too, if they get their opportunitie.</p>
               <p>And for their language in the exerciſe of their offices, they ſpeak half in the language of Aſhdod, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.24.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93696:14"/>like the mingled people, <hi>Jere.</hi> 50.37. of many religions, yea of any ſave the true, becauſe thats no friend to them, and their functions.</p>
               <p>But becauſe they boaſt ſo much of their deſcent from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, but are found lyers, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.2. We will (by their leave) take a walke further through their Orchards, and taſte of their ripeſt fruits and try what ſoyle they taſte of, whether the fruits of the functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, or of Antichriſts functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and offices.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When Chriſt was to leave his deare Diſciples in a troubleſome world, he left his peace with them for a Legacy, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.27. to comfort them in all their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and commands them to love one another becauſe the world would hate them, as it hated him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.17. But theſe Prelates by their vexatious offices, ſuffer Chriſts Miniſters and ſervants to have little peace, and leſſe love, hate them <hi>Cain</hi>-like, even to the death; but a Papiſt is a brave companion for them, at Table, in Coach, in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and familiaritie, in all their affaires; as <hi>Blackwell</hi> the Prieſt ſaid long agoe, I wonder, ſaid he, of what religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Biſhops are, us they perſecute becauſe we are Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, but they hate a Puritane, and of the two, they love us the better: and how that love is encreaſed, ſhews they are birds of the black feather, (like the Raven that after ſhe once got out of the Arke never returned) ſo, as ſoone as ever one of theſe Prelates is got into a Biſhops Sea, they are flowne out of the Church, the infection of the fowle neſt like the plague of Leproſie, ſtrikes them, ſome ſooner, ſome later, ſo as they take to their wings and flie home to Rome, the reſting place of their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minds, and who can blame them (for it is the nature of the office, to be like and love their mother) and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther help them forward to her.
<q>Sic canibus catulos ſimiles ſic matribus haedos. <note place="margin">Virgil.</note>
                  </q> Of this their flight to Rome, ſee it clearly in their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93696:14"/>of reconciling us to their Mother, and others of them not ſo skilfull in the art, as forward in the flight, labouring openly to reduce us wholly to Rome, <hi>Ex pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſo tanquam ex officio,</hi> as the very nature of the office ſo to doe, to beget and bring forth many children to their mother, ther's ſome plaine dealing in theſe if they doe not turne with the winde, which now troubles them in their flight and work. For as birds nodding their heads, let us ſee which way they are flying, ſo the Prelates and their ſonnes of the Church by their nodding Eaſtward, let us ſee their ayme is Rome-ward. And when in this late Epiſcopall quarrell with the <hi>Scots</hi> by their ſole inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, they ſaw a neceſſitie of open flight to the Popes and Papiſts ayde, or loſe their fat Biſhopricks, expecting this faire ſeaſon for their flight, they were ſo ready for it, as they had their excuſes ready before hand. [That if Popery came into <hi>England</hi> againe, the Puritanes were the cauſe of it
<note place="margin">* Prelate of <hi>Dureſme.</hi>
                  </note>] as <hi>Tenterton</hi> Steeple is the cauſe of <hi>Goodwin Sands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt would not meddle with the Magiſtrates au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in dividing the Inheritance, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.13.14. as without compaſſe of his office, his kingdome was not of this world, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.36. Theſe Prelates are wholly world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, muſt be chiefe in Parliaments, in the Kings Councells, in chiefe offices. Lord Chancellour, Lord Treaſurer, &amp;c. and overſway all the affaires in Court and Countrey, as if by their pretended divine Authoritie, they had full Commiſſion from Chriſt to divide the world amongſt them, and Pope-like challenge all the Kingdomes of the world, and the ends of the Earth for a poſſeſſion, from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. Thus like Foxes on the mountaines, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.4. on mountaines of prey (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.4.) mounted in their High Commiſſions and Courts, like to the Mountaines of Leopards, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.8. they prey upon all that come neare them; fine and impriſon, and ceaſe on mens lands and eſtates, and divide many an Orphans inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt the greateſt Prophet bome of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93696:15"/>
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.28. his cloathing was but courſe, <hi>Camells haire and a letherne girdle about his loynes,</hi> his dyet but homely, <hi>Locuſts and wilde honey,</hi> Mat. 3.4. Theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates ruffle it bravely in ſilks and velvets, and pure Lawne ſleeves, like Butchers ever ready to have their hands in blood, and the meaneſt ſon of the Church muſt have a ſilken girdle with a roſe up to his noſe, as if his pride were his perſume, and for his dyet it muſt be dainty fare, no Butchers meate, Pheaſant and Veniſon for their weake ſtomacks (oppreſt with ſtudies but of what kind? <hi>Quare</hi>) waſht downe with the moſt delitious wines. As they! ſo their Prebends muſt keepe reſidence at the Biſhops Sea, (but not at their Pariſhes) to feaſt the Clergie while the flockes are ſtarving with cold ſervice of a <hi>St Iohn. Whoſe belly is their God, whoſe glory their ſhame, who minde earthly things</hi> Phil. 3.19. Of whom that of the Monkes of old is verified.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>O monachi veſtri ſt machi ſunt amphora bacchi,</l>
                  <l>Vos eſtis deus est teſtis turpiſſima peſtis.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Paul</hi> accounted all things loſſe for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt, and counted them but dung, and for to gaine Chriſt ſuffered the loſſe of all things, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. Theſe Prelates account all gaine they by their offices gather, and pick out of mens purſes by fines and taxes and illegall courſes to gaine Antichriſt. Witneſſe <hi>Pauls,</hi> and ſuch like good works they cry up, to make gorgeous Temples, neſts for Idolls, Images, Altars, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixes, and rich Ornaments, baits and allurements to carnall ſenſe, to draw the ignorant to their mothers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications in her old rotten age. And for loſſe, before they will loſe any thing of their dignitie to gaine Chriſt, they will hazard the loſſe of Chriſt and all theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to Rome and Spaine or France.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>Paul, Beloved brother</hi> theſe like Spaniſh Donns, muſt be called of their brethren, My Lord, your Grace, and Right reverend Fathers, and be bowed to like Princes.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93696:15"/>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Peter</hi> is content to ſtoop ſo low as to write himſelfe in the loweſt ſtyle belonging to his function, <hi>An Elder,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. Theſe on the contrary aſſume the higheſt ſtyles of Earles in their writing; as <hi>Will: Cant, Tho: Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſme, Joſ: Exon.</hi> Exonored of his ſpectacles in his old dayes, for he hath eyes for other men to ſee with, but it is at blinde man buff. But thankes be to God we can ſee ſo much with our owne eyes, that they are begun to fall, when <hi>Joſ: Exon</hi> is fallen ſo low, as from a Father to a ſon of the Church, with the meaneſt Prieſt, as having too long lorded it over his brethren.</p>
               <p n="7">7. We are commanded to feare God, honour the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change, <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.31. Theſe Prelates are ſo Cock-ſure in their warme neſts as in the clefts of the Rocks, that they ſhew little feare of God or his revenging Juſtice, as if they had writ over their gates, Mock God, Mock Devill, Babel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like at defiance with both; <hi>I ſit as a Queene and ſhall never be moved,</hi> Iſa. 47. Apoc. 18. And as the Spaniard had writ over the gates of the <hi>Buſſ</hi> in <hi>Brabant</hi> or <hi>Boſſ-le due,</hi> this blaſphemous Inſcription, <hi>When the Buſſ is taken God ſhall be a lyar;</hi> as I have heard of credible hands; but God made the <hi>Hollander</hi> blot out that blaſphemy, &amp; left them lyars. 2. For honour of the King, they ſo farre obſerve it as their own honour is concerned, and in the firſt place regarded, the other muſt but ſerve it. 3. And becauſe they have not honour enough, or be high enough, they are buſie medling with Papiſts and Jeſuites, the great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts of the world for changes of Kings and Kingdomes and States, turning them up-ſide downe, to change our Lawes, our Religion, and liberties, and lives too; and to plant the Land with Spaniards, as we had found ere now, if the Spaniſh Fleet laſt yeare had once landed, but bleſſed be God, who without us prevented it, and broke that devilliſh deſigne, and gives us faire warning to take heed to ſuch Prelates, ſo officious in their offices, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſures ſo with the Jeſuites, alwayes digging under ground and working changes. They have ſucked all the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93696:16"/>nouriſhment to higher advancement that this State can afford them, and ſo full ripe for a Miter and a Cardinalls cap, which here are not, that tis high time they were gone where they may have them, rather than they bring Rome and Spaine to us to obtaine them.</p>
               <p>Theſe are a taſte of ſome of their ripeſt fruits we finde as yet, though doubtleſſe others may finde many moe, but bleſſed be God who hath a little ſhaken their fruits that now our hoggs doe eate them.</p>
               <p>Yet certainly Right Honourable Worthies now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament, if this tree of Epiſcopacy none of Gods planting, but a plant of Sathans planting, ſprung up in the dunghill of the Papacy, naturally bringing forth theſe bitter fruits, be of you ſuffered to ſtand but till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſolſtice of warme Sun-ſhine come over from Rome or Spaine, wee ſhall finde more dangerous and deadly fruits of it ere long, <hi>Acherontam vendo.</hi> What miſchiefes will they not hatch ere they loſe their gainfull offices, their pleaſant loftie dignities; will never be content in a lower condition; nay, before they quit their ground, as ſtout Souldiers and Champions of the Romiſh Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, they will be buſie under ground with the Jeſuites, the chiefe Maſters of fire-works, to ſpring a mine of ſome horrid plot of a new invention, to make all theſe three Kingdomes ſhake: as ſome of their excommunicate bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Scotland</hi> bolted out of late; alas their hearts were ſo heavy as they muſt vent ſome wind rather than burſt. Are not theſe brave Spirits will venture upon ſuch hard ſervice for their Maſter? The King of Spaine we heare ſtands in need of ſuch artiſts to blow up the walls of Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, tis pitty he ſhould want them.</p>
               <p>And therefore Right Honourable, beſtirre your ſelves betime to meete thoſe underminers with a countermine, to ſpring them and their works together: theres no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of ſafetie to our King and his poſteritie, and all theſe three Kingdomes, ſo linked together in ſo many bands, as we muſt of neceſſitie ſtand and fall together. I love to ſpeak plaine Engliſh, and think none will blame
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93696:16"/>me of temeritie or raſhneſſe at this time, but ſuch as ſpeak too much Spaniſh. I doe but the office of a Beacon, which is <hi>Monſtrare, non ducere nec docere,</hi> to ſhew the approaches of dangers, if you prevent not. Men uſe not to blame him who lyes Sentinel <hi>perdue</hi> as a loſt man, for giving warning of danger.</p>
               <p>Though now it might ſeeme we have enough of the Prelates windie divine authoritie, now found none of Gods planting as by their fruits at Chriſts command we have tryed and found them: and therefore nothing now wanting, but the execution of his own ſentence, to be rooted out, which we now expect by the diligent hand of this Honourable Parliament. Yet may I not paſſe till I have met with <hi>Tho: Dureſme</hi> in particular, becauſe he hath deceived many, both Papiſts and Proteſtants in their expectations, and by his leave, I would faine love my Religion and Countrey above his dignitie or regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie more fit for one of the Kings Sons than any Prelate, and therefore for his cauſe we will have one bout more about the office.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> VIII.</head>
               <p>Thoſe offices and that government in the Church, which nouriſh ignorance and blindneſſe, an idle, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and unſound Miniſtery, perſecute our Religion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, and the orthodox Preachers and profeſſors of it, and cheriſh and countenance Popery and Papiſts, and their dangerous meeting and Maſſes, are not of Chriſt, but of Antichriſt. But ſuch are the offices and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dioceſan Biſhops and the reſt of that rable. <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> not of Chriſt but of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>The Major if they will cavill at here, ſee it made good <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. And ſo we proceed to the proofe of the Minor; which if it be all made good in the office and officers of <hi>Tho: Dureſme,</hi> accounted one of the beſt in the bunch, it may be worth ſomething, to move the reſt in modeſty to take it home to them without more adoe.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:93696:17"/>
               <p n="1">1. For ignorance and blindneſſe, an ignorant idle and unſound Miniſtery, perſecution of Religion eſtabliſhed, and the orthodox preachers and profeſſors of it, though too conformable, his dioceſſe and government may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter challenge the Metropolitane precedency, than his kingly regalitie: none of them, not <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Cant.</hi> or the winged little <hi>Wren,</hi> hath flowne more ſwiftly home to Rome in their practiſes, at leaſt he may deſerve the place next to them, none of them h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d their Seas of ſound Preachers, (as if they were Pirates to the Prelates office) as he hath done, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> few puritane Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers (as they terme them) whom his worſe reputed predeceſſors, had left in that dioceſſe, and ſome others brought in by men well affected to preaching in that poore ignorant Countrey, (an object of this honourable Parliaments pitty) he hath had the honour to root them out. So as in one poore County of Northumberland and towne of Newcaſtle, in about ſeventy two or more Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes (beſides Chappells) whereof divers livings of two three and foure hundred <hi>per annum,</hi> as we are credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by ſome of the Inhabitants of credit, ther's ſcarce a Miniſter left that is not a ſuperſtitious innovator, or not popiſh, and Arminian, or that make conſcience of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, but as they pleaſe at their leaſure, or regard the peoples ſoules, but prey upon their fleeces, and poll their purſes,
<note place="margin">Auguſt. de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore.</note> like ſoule-murtherers, as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> calls them. And ſome Gentlemen who have been at the charge of keeping godly Preachers, have been robd of them by theſe Wolves ravening, that lay waſte Countryes and Congregations; ſuch rule he keepes. If <hi>Tho: Dureſms</hi> houſe were ſo kept as he hath kept Gods, there would be nothing but hungar and hard walls, and cold entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his fat Prebends: and who knows but the Lord may ere long ſend as much famine amongſt them, as they have had feaſting, and the poore flocks ſtarving. And for his County Palatine of <hi>Dureſme,</hi> that ſoyle can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beare ſound preaching and Preachers, no plants for his Palatinate, but if you will talke of fat parſons and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93696:17"/>fat Prebends, pluraliſts, and tot quots, &amp;c. his ſoyle affords as good ſtore of theſe fat Cattle, like kine of <hi>Baſhan</hi> (as it doth of fat Oxen) neſtling in fat livings of foure, five, ſix, and ſeven hundred pound <hi>per annum,</hi> and as full ſtall-fed as any in the Land: moſt of which livings have been of late ſupplyed by his kinſmen and others his friends, brought in by him into chiefe offices, popiſh and ſuperſtitious, of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cozens</hi> garbe, ſo as he hath out gone his predeceſſors herein. In ſumma, <hi>Will: Cant.</hi> or little <hi>Wrenns</hi> dioceſſes cannot paralell his, for a crue of dumbe doggs, Sir <hi>Iohns,</hi> alchouſe-keepers, prophane antick fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, more fit for a ſtage than a pulpit and other popiſh Arminian Mountebancks, that vend the Italian wares as faſt as any in the Land. So that in this particular, he is the greateſt ſoule-murtherer in the Land without the mountaines of <hi>Wales,</hi> woe will be to him for it; and for oppreſſion, and Incloſures, &amp;c. his poore Palatines ſay, that their caſe is little better than the poore <hi>Iriſh</hi> Cram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macrees under the Lord Lieutenant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For Superſtition, let his Cathedrall and Sea of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> witneſſe, and be viſited, it will be found as well fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered as the <hi>Wrens</hi> neſt: and for <hi>Tho. Dureſme</hi> himſelfe, he is ſo zealous of Altar-worſhip, and ſuch fopperies, as before he miſſe of his devotion, he will duck to a Tombe, in ſtead of an Altar, its good to be ſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For countenancing Popery, and cheriſhing Papiſts, his Chancellour, Archdeacon, and Officialls, in riding their Circuits, make theſe their chiefe familiars: but for puritanes, they toſſe and tumble them in their Courts, till they be wearied out of their callings, and Countrey too, <hi>Tho: Dureſme</hi> himſelfe threatning to rid the Land of them, till then, ſaith he, it will never be at reſt. And if the times had not ſuddenly turned above all humane ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, its moſt probable by many prodigious ſignes, that the firſt bloody maſſacre of all that but favoured our religion as well as the putitanes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> be thankfull to God, thou haſt ſcap't a ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging.</note> ſhould have begun in his Dioceſſe, in Northumberland, and towne of <hi>New aſtle,</hi> full ſtuft with his palatine Papiſts, it ſeemes, to that end,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93696:18"/>and thoſe of the moſt dangerous in the Land, never mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted till the <hi>Scots</hi> ſcattered them.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Tho: Dureſme</hi> amongſt his palatine Souldiers, moſt Papiſts, in theſe late Epiſcopall broyles was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to have in his Coach with him one of the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Papiſts in the North, &amp; fit to be one of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Warre in his regalitie, and in that Epiſcopall quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with the <hi>Scots;</hi> which being publickly taken notice of, was very offenſive to many, and ſcandalous to his Majeſties government, and to his pretended divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to ſee <hi>Tho: Dureſme</hi> ſo accompanied: I know not what he can ſay to this, but that he left his Rochet and office at his Sea of <hi>Dureſme,</hi> and now in his regalitie no more Biſhop; as the Lutherane Prieſts in Germany, when they goe to a feaſt, lay downe their black gowne, ſaying, Lie thou there Prieſt, now Ile be as joviall as the beſt of you: ſo <hi>Camelion</hi>-like change into any colour.</p>
               <p>He alſo nouriſhes in his Dioceſſe a company of popiſh-Arminian Miniſters, of <hi>Wil: Cant<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</hi> chiefe correſpondence, by whom (as by the like in other parts of the Land) he hath had conſtant intelligence of all matters, and of all the perſons and families that favour our religion in thoſe parts, that once they might get a day to rid the world of them.</p>
               <p>He alſo connives at dangerous meetings of the moſt ſtirring Papiſts, their baptiſmes and night burialls, with tapers, and torches, and bells ringing, but without the uſe of the Service Booke, and againſt their owne Canons: whereby it appeares, their Service Booke and Canons ſerve onely againſt puritanes, and muſt not be diſcharged againſt Papiſts. So as the chiefe Townes of his dioceſſe, are of late become dennes of Papiſts, and places of reſort to their meetings and Maſſes, and of traffique and trade in their Books and Beads and Romiſh Merchandize.</p>
               <p>All which conſidered, he may be ſaid to have given the lye to all his former works and writings againſt the Papiſts. So that it may be verified of him, that he is the greateſt Papiſt friend that ever came in <hi>Dureſme</hi> ſince our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93696:18"/>reformation. See here how the Antichriſtian office hath blaſted all his fruits, and made him the ſhame of his old age, and of that pretended divine office of Epiſcopacy, which now the Lord will have made naked to the world. And all this flowes out of the dunghill foundation and filthy nature of the office, ſerving principally to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Antichriſts kingdome, to waſte the Church and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the offices of Chriſt. So as it would ſeeme that Epiſcopacy now is come to its full height and ripeneſſe in this Land: it hath ever ſince our reformation oppoſed Chriſts kingly office, as its mortall enemy, whereby its growne to this height at this day to overthrow his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall and Prieſtly offices alſo: that all the world may ſee, as in the Sun-ſhine, that the offices and government of the Prelacy, are meerly Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p>By this time, I thinke, they have done, and ſo have we with their divine Authoritie, as having too long raked in that dunghill, and therefore we come now to the iſſue. That ſince they cannot reckon up their genealogie from <hi>Levie,</hi> (from another divine authoritie than the Canon Law) let them as polluted be put from the Prieſthood, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7 64. Thus did good <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and the Princes, true patternes of reformation before us. The Lord put into the hearts of his Majeſtie, and the Worthies of this Honourable Parliament, to follow their example, and to clenſe the Land of this polluted Prieſthood and filthy dunghill offices of Antichriſtian Authoritie, which hath ſo long eclipſed the Goſpels light, and the name and fame of our Nations glory in the eyes of all the reformed world, who with the bulk and body of Popery, have alſo caſt off this heavie yoke and regiment of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy.</p>
               <p>Therefore as not compatible with Chriſts kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and ſcepter of his World, with Our royall Kings Authoritie, our Sions peace, and Kingdomes glory in the flouriſhing of Chriſts Kingdome. Wee hope this Honourable Parliament, will no longer ſuffer this tree of Sathans planting to ſtand, but root it out, according
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93696:19"/>to Chriſts owne ſentence and will,
<note place="margin">Away with all the reverend Fathers, and their ſonnes of the Church, with all their trumpery.</note> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.16.20. and 15.13. Cut off from <hi>Babell</hi> roote and branch, ſon and nephew, name and remnant, deſtroy her utterly, let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of her be left, <hi>Ier.</hi> 50.26. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.22. thinke it not to be ſufficient (for you will not finde it ſo) to curbe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency, and lop off the loftie ſpreading branches of this tree of Epiſcopacy, when the Lord Jeſus hath ſaid it ſhall be rooted out, and hath laid the axe of his Word to the roote, and will have it cut downe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10. and <hi>cap.</hi> 17 20. <hi>and eaſt into the fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doe you Right Honourable and Noble workmen of the Lord, take it as a choiſe bleſſing, that now the Lord hath by a Parliament put into your hands the axe of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to be alſo layd to the root of this tree, and count it your greateſt honour, every one of you, to lend it a blow, and it will ſuddenly fall; God hath done his part, if you ſet to yours, he will put ſtrength into your hands againſt all difficulties;
<note place="margin">Ioſ. 1.9.</note> be ſtrong and of good courage, theſe Cananites ſhall be but bread for you, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.9. for the Lord is with you: to remove mountaines of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties that lye in your way, if yee faithfully truſt to his aſſiſtance, yee ſhall ſay to theſe mountaines, remove and they ſhall be caſt into the Sea, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.22. Plow up the very roots, and weed the ground, the land of it, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it be left, and the place will be a fruitfull ſoyle. Their pluralities and fat Livings they have encloſed and impaled to ſerve their eaſe, their pomp and pleaſures, will be as Sharon, Sheepfolds for Chriſt to feed his flocks by his Shepheards tents, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.8. Therefore doe not this work of the Lord negligently; if you curbe their greatneſſe and lop the branches never ſo much, and leave the root, the office in the ground, within their warme neſts and Epiſcopall Seas, though you ſhall binde it downe with Iron bands, and lay upon it all the weight of good Lawes you can poſſibly deviſe, it will through the ſent of the puddle water,
<note place="margin">Iob 14.9.</note> bud and ſpring againe next ſeaſon, and bring forth more bitter fruits than ever: Epiſcopacy, (not the perſons is the root of all our evills)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93696:19"/>it is that uncleane bird we ſpoke of that is flowne out of the Arke, and will never be drawne to your lure, never be diſciplined. Set up Chriſts Kingdome, and it will bring in Arm-fulls of bleſſings to us and our poſteritie, and make our Kingdome flouriſh. If men were but once acquainted with that royall Scepter and government, his ſweet and eaſie yoake, they would quickly ſee the benefit of reformation, and what a heavy yoke the Prelacy hath been to our King and State and whole Land.</p>
               <p>Now having ſhewed the unlawfulneſſe and evills of the offices, and tryed them both by the Word and by their fruits to be Antichriſtian. If any yet will be ſo ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous againſt ſo cleare light to open their mouthes to plead for Epiſcopacy, &amp; oppoſe the ſetting up of Chriſts Kingly office in his throne and glory, we will ſhew them the danger of it for their warning, in two ſhorts Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> IX.</head>
               <p>If the Prelates and their officers in the exerciſe of their unlawfull offices, doe many things in the worſhip of God without warrant of the Word of God, they are guilty of the ſinne and puniſhment of <hi>Nadab,</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi> But ſo doe the Prelates and their Officers: as witneſſe the whole ſource of their ſuperſtitions, and mens inventions of old, and late inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated abhominations of Jewiſh Popiſh and Heatheniſh fopperies and Ceremonies, which they have brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worſhip of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> they are guilty of the like ſinne and puniſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>Argument</hi> X.</head>
               <p>If <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu, Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> were ſo ſtrangely puniſhed for once preſuming (in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their lawfull offices) to doe that which they had
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93696:20"/>no warrant for. What may the Prelates and all their confederates expect, but unheard of plagues, and ſtrange puniſhments, for not once but many yeares, (after many warnings, and againſt light and knowledge abounding) doing many things in the worſhip of God without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the word of God, and that in the exerciſe of their unlawfull offices. As thoſe periſhed wonderfully in the withſtanding <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the word of God, ſhall not theſe Prelates and their partakers periſh much more wonderfully in the withſtanding of Chriſt, farre greater than <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> were ſo ſtrangely puniſhed as fire from heaven conſumed them, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.1. and the Earth opened her mouth and ſwallowed up quick, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and all their company, in the ſight of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and all the people; as we may ſee at large, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo</hi> the uſurping Prelates and all their partakers, may look out for ſome ſtrange unheard of puniſhment, from the Lord of Hoaſts waiting for them and all that joyne with them in oppoſing Chriſt in his Kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and diſcipline. An end is come, the end is come, it watcheth for them, <hi>behold it is come,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7 6. It is recorded to all poſteritie to the worlds end, as a brand of infamy upon all thoſe that did partake in that oppoſition of <hi>Moſes; They periſhed in the gainſaying of Core,</hi> Jude 11. Let all that plead for and partake in the unlawfull offices and practiſes of the Prelates, take heed to this in time: for the Lord is a ſtrong God, who judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the whore and all her bratts and abhominations, <hi>Partake not in her ſinnes, least yee partake in her plagues,</hi> Apoc. 18.4.8.</p>
               <q>Come out of the tents of theſe wicked men, <bibl>
                     <hi>Numb. 16.26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The maine objection for Prelacy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> Oh but (ſay ſome) we have had godly Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and many learned men that have been Dioceſan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops as theſe are, and their government been long ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93696:20"/>and Religion under it wonderfully flouriſhed as in any Nation; And many worthy Inſtruments both in the Magiſtracy and Miniſtery, who have ſubmitted to this government, which ſure they would not have done if it were unlawfull and Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Church and faithfull Miniſters have not all light at once or by one inſtrument, or yet by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy lights, the remembrance of whom is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and therefore as we would not detract any thing of their deſervings from them, ſo muſt we not ſtick faſt in their footſteps and goe no further. For ſtill daily more and greater light of the Goſpells brightneſſe is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected till the fulneſſe of the Gentiles light come in, and be ſwallowed up in the Jewes fulneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12. Chriſt Jeſus comes to his people as the Sunne ariſes, firſt, theres the dawning, then the darkneſſe expelled, and ſtill brighter light, till the Sunne ſhine in his full ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Theſe worthy Martyrs that were Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Biſhops, in the dawning of the Goſpels light after a long darkſome night of Popery, muſt be confeſſed to riſe up in their Rochets out of the Papacy, and ſaw not preſently into the unlawfulneſſe of their office, yet ſome of them did and reſigned, as <hi>Latimer;</hi> but they ſet themſelves againſt the moſt cleare corruptions in doctrine and worſhip, ſo farre as they had light; as for Diſcipline it was ſo ſwept away in that great deluge of Popery, that no footſteps of it were to be ſeene in thoſe times, or if any thing of it, yet but as the blinde man in the Goſpell recovering his ſight, ſaw men walking like trees, very darkly and confuſedly.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, As their ſight grew ſomewhat clearer, they ſaw into a godly diſcipline in the primitive Church, at which they aymed, as in the Preface to the Common prayer book at the Commination may be ſeene, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes they ſaw into another diſcipline than that they had amongſt them, and brought with them out of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, and is uſed to this day, therefore not the right diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93696:21"/>and yet that primitive diſcipline, it is as probi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they ſaw at a great diſtance even then, and ſo left it to be ſearched out more clearly of the following genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and if they did ſee it any thing clearly, and if any thing hindered their light of breaking out into a more full reformation, we may thank even the Dioceſan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops for it, whoſe love of preheminence as ours now was the chiefe let in reformation in thoſe times, as our Hiſtories ſhew. So as we have little cauſe to boaſt of Biſhops, as inſtruments of our reſormation, if we were well acquainted with the ſtate of thoſe times, and what hinderers of Reformation the Biſhops were, yea ſome of them that after ſuffered as Martyrs in Queene <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> time.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Some Biſhops ſuffering as Martyrs after their morning light was clouded againe with hot perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions and ſtormes ariſing, even out of the ſame Seas they were in, by the changing of the winde in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time, is no more an argument from their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome that their office was good, than if a Cardinall in Rome or Spaine ſhould profeſſe the Goſpell, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for it: his office were nevertheleſſe ſtill Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, When theſe ſtormes were over, and a greater light broke out in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, of a brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sunne-ſhine, multitudes of learned and godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters began to ſee clearly the foundation of Babell lay cloſe and unſeene in the office of Epiſcopacy, and in the keeping out Chriſts Kingly office eſpecially, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preached, writ, diſputed, and ſuffered for it, even as Martyrs of thoſe times by the tyranny of the Prelates who ſtill oppoſe it to this day; as witneſſe <hi>Cartwright, Parker, Fenner, Childerley, Chatterton, Traverſe, Reinolds,</hi> and a many more; and at King <hi>James</hi> his firſt entrance about a thouſand Miniſters ſtood for Reformation of the Epiſcopall government, and for ſetting up of Chriſts Kingly office, who were in a ſew yeares waſted and ſpent and baniſhed and devoured of theſe ravenous Wolves,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93696:21"/>wives and children undone, and many families ſcattered, eſtates ruined for oppoſing this prelaticall office and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſo as little cauſe have we to boaſt of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, it hath been a bloody office to this day. Alſo many living yet can witneſſe how a reformation hath been ſtill petitioned for to Parliaments, even to this day: though with no ſucceſſe, becauſe their ſins were not full, nor ours repented of and reformed.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, For many worthy inſtruments in Magiſtracy and Miniſtery, ſubmitting to Epiſcopall government. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Divine examples, (but not humane) doe binde the Conſcience, and make their practiſes rules to us; ſecondly, the Churches of a whole Nation, yea of many Nations, abounding with men of excellent parts, both in the Magiſtracy and Miniſtery, may yet long neglect ſome of Gods Ordinances, partly through ignorance, partly for want of aſſiſtance of the ſupreme Magiſtrate, as all the times of the Judges, and many good Kings, even from <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the time of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> the feaſt of keeping of boothes was neglected. Becauſe, firſt, theres much naturall blindneſſe in the beſt men: ſecondly, the Church often too careleſſe in ſome weighty things: thirdly, men are ready to ſit downe ere their work be half done, ſoone weary in ſo great and publick works as Reformation is: the ſpirit is willing, but the fleſh is weake. Thus as they of old long neglected the feaſt of boothes, ſo have we too long neglected Chriſts diſcipline and government: the Lord pardon it.</p>
               <p>Seventhly and laſtly, for the flouriſhing of Religion under the Prelates government, we have no cauſe to thanke them; they have alway perſecuted the light and life of it, and done their beſt to put out the light, and to bring in an Egyptian darkneſſe againe: ſecondly, it hath been thoſe they have moſt perſecuted who have ſpread the greateſt light, for a perſecuted light is ever the brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, which ſhews it to be of God, and like to him, though darkneſſe comprehend it not; to him be glory that we have any light after ſo hot perſecutions, and ſo many ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93696:22"/>this is a ſigne our perſecuted light ſhall prevaile: <hi>Tandem bona cauſa triumphat,</hi> was that renowned old Duke of Saxons Motto in all his bitter troubles with <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Thirdly, though ſome ſee it not, ſo ſleepy-headed in their eaſe and pleaſures, they little regard the hazard Gods Ark is in, yet others that have watched long in the long winter night of the Churches troubles, for the daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the day of deliverance, have found ill fruits of flouriſhing of Religion, and ſeene a great decay of the power of godlineſſe theſe many yeares paſt, and many Miniſters and profeſſors fallen, ſome in following the ſway of the times for worldly things, others through pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillanimitie of ſpirit, into great decay of gifts and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, all for want of Chriſts diſcipline, to keepe all men in their ſeverall ſtations, and active in obedience; and to hedge in the Church from the inroades of enemies. The Lord teach us the uſe and benefit of, and open our eyes to ſee the want of, &amp; pardon our ſo long neglect of Chriſts Kingly office.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion of all.</head>
               <p>Since now the pretended divine Authoritie of the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy is fayled in the foundation, and left them no foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but in the filthy dunghill of the Canon Law of the Popes Authoritie, exalted above the Scriptures, in which they Mother like have built their neſts, as in the clefts of the rocks of the ſeven hilled Citie. And they in Gods juſt judgement ſo blinded and of late confounded in their Councells, as to caſt off his Majeſties royall Authoritie, by which they have ſtood too long: and not a little tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched upon, they deſerve to finde and feele, that <hi>He beares not the ſword in vaine,</hi> Rom. 13.4. but is Gods <hi>vindex</hi> of his own and ſubjects wrongs many wayes, ſo eſpecially in oppoſing Chriſt ſo long in his Kingly office, and now at laſt in all his offices. As they by the abuſe of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſword have ruined many, ſo by the ſame ſword let them periſh; <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93696:22"/>blood be ſhed; He that killeth with the ſword, ſhall be killed with the ſword,</hi> Gen. 9.6. Apoc. 13.10. Matth. 26.52. the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, and we waite the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of it. The Lord put into the hearts of our royall King, and of this honourable Parliament, to fulfill his will upon Babell and all her bratts and abhominations, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jerem. 50.24.26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I have laid a ſnare for thee, and thou art alſo taken O Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, and waſt not aware, thou art ſound and alſo caught, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt ſtriven againſt the Lord. Tread her in hèapes, deſtroy her utterly, let nothing of her be left.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The benefits of Reformation of Diſcipline.</head>
               <p>Then ſhall Chriſts workmen with great alacritie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to build the houſe of God, which theſe men have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced and defiled, and make a beautifull habitation for the Lord Jeſus to dwell and delight in, and great ſhall be his glory in the midſt of us, in preſence and protection. Then ſhall our eyes ſee our King in his glory on his throne, and our Jeruſalem in peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.17.20.</p>
               <p>Then alſo ſhall King <hi>Charles</hi> his throne be more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious than any his predeceſſors; then ſhall Judgement and Juſtice flow forth as a mighty River, to ſweep away all ſinne and wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall our King be to the Juſt as raine upon the graſſe new mowen;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 72.</note> the Mountaines ſhall bring forth peace, and the little hills righteouſneſſe; Court and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſhall flouriſh, the Land ſhall bring forth her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and God even our God ſhall bleſſe us, and all the ends of the Earth ſhall ſeare him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67.6. When they heare and ſee what great things he will doe for us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:93696:23"/>
               <head>A ſhort appendix touching Diſcipline.</head>
               <p>Since in this great and honourable High Court of Parliament, every ſubject is ſo concerned as bound to ſubmit to what ſhall be therein eſtabliſhed, therefore as a member and well-wiſher of the well-fare of the whole body, I crave leave for a word or two concerning diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Since tis now in every mans mouth, what forme of diſcipline we ſhall have, when the Prelaticall, as none of Chriſts, ſhall be juſtly aboliſhed. Which ſeems to me to upbraid the ignorance and unthankfulneſſe of this age, (the fruits of Epiſcopacy) as if men in the Sun-ſhine ſhould complaine of darkneſſe: or as if the Spirit of Chriſt which deſcended upon the Apoſtles, teaching all things, and leading them into all truth, ſhould have left them wandring at randome without direction in governing the houſe of God; or yet left it arbitrary to mens ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall minds, humours, and frames. The Scriptures are full and plentifully furniſhed with inſtructions for the whole frame and faſhions of the houſe of GOD, which all brought together and ſet up, would be a beautifull ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture; it is the tabernacle of God with men, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.3. walking in the midſt of them,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.17. It were a piece of heavens happineſſe to ſee it advanced in the ſame form Chriſt hath appointed and his Apoſtles practiſed and inſtituted in all the Churches, to be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall to the worlds end. All I have to ſay in one word, tis that I would conſent to; keepe cloſe to that patterne, and beware of the ſeverall frames of mens braines, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne the Church by humane policy, after the manner of earthly Kingdomes and States, which was the firſt thing brought in the plague of Epiſcopacy, and will ſtill leave a back-dore to papall tyranny in the Church of God: from which we can never be ſecured untill Chriſts own government be eſtabliſhed, tis his own Scepter muſt rule and no inventions of men or Angels, if poſſibly they could be conſulted with.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
